Chapter 11.
The Pacific.
When gliding by the Bashi Isles, we emerged at last upon the great South
Sea. Were it not for other things, I could have greeted my dear Pacific with
uncounted thanks, for now the long supplication of my youth was answered,
that serene ocean rolled eastwards from me a thousand leagues of blue.
There is one knows not what sweet mystery about this sea whose gentle
awful stirring seem to speak of some hidden soul beneath like those fabled
undulations of the Ephesian sod over the buried evangelist St. John and meat it
is that over these sea pastures, wide rolling watery prairies and potter's
fields of all four continents the wave should rise and fall and eb and flow
unceasingly. For here millions of mixed shades and shadows, drowned dreams,
somnambulisms, rearies. All that we call lives and souls lie dreaming, dreaming
still, tossing like slumberers in their beds. the ever rolling waves, but made
so by their restlessness.
To any meditative magian rover, this serene Pacific, once beheld, must ever
after be the sea of his adoption. It rolls the midmost waters of the world,
the Indian Ocean and Atlantic being but its arms. The same waves wash the moles
of the new built Californian towns, but yesterday planted by the recentest race
of men, and leave the faded but still gorgeous skirts of Asiatic lands older
than Abraham, while all between float milky ways of coral isles and low-lying
endless unknown archipelos and impenetrable Japans. Thus this
mysterious divine Pacific zones the world's whole bulk about makes all
coasts one bay to it seems the tidebeating heart of earth lifted by
those eternal swells you needs must own the seductive god bowing your head to pan
but few thoughts of pan stirred Ahab's brain as standing like an iron statue at
his accustom place beside the mizenrigging with one nostril he
unthinking ly snuffed the sugary musk from the bashy isles, in whose sweet
woods mild lovers must be walking, and with the other consciously inhaled the
salt breath of the new found sea, that sea in which the hated white whale must
even then be swimming. Launched at length upon these almost final waters,
and gliding towards the Japanese cruising ground, the old man's purpose
intensified itself. His firm lips met like the lips of a vice. The delta of
his forehead's veins swelled like overladen brooks. In his very sleep, his
ringing cry ran through the vaulted hull. Stern all the white whale spouts thick blood.